A Guide to the Susan Glaspell Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #7629
Susan Glaspell Collection 1912-1922
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
7629
18 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Deposit 20 July 1964
Item Listing
- Manuscripts
  - Poem, " Though stone be broken ", 1912 April; TMs, 3 p.
  - Poem, " The shining rocks ", ca. 1922; TMs, 1 p.
    [Dedicated to Arthur Davison Ficke. ]
  - Poem, " The shining rocks ", ca. 1922; TMs, 2 p.
    [In corrected form.]
  - Extracts from the Parnassus Letters, ca. 1922; TMs, 2 p.
    [Collected by Edna Kenton. ]
- Letters
  - George Cram Cook, Greece, to Edna Kenton, 1922 May 4; AL, 6 p.
    [Mentions Delphi, The Rock of the Sybil, geology of the area, etc.; includes 2 poems, "I lay on the rocks in the cool gorge.. ." and "Beat against me, East Wind.. ."]
  - George Cram Cook to Edna Kenton, 1922 June 8; AL, 2 p.
    [Gives her a copy of his "semi-drunken" letter to "Fitzie" [Mary Eleanor Fitzgerald]; remarks unflatteringly about Fitzgerald's character.]
  - Edna Kenton to Blanche, 1922 June 22; TLS, 1 p.
    [Writes of George Cram Cook 's sail to Greece; discusses closing of the theater and renting it to a different group of players for one year; refers to Jane Street Church episode; expresses gratitude for help on
    Chains of Dew
    . ]
  - George Cram Cook to Edna Kenton, 1922 July 10-23; AL, 3 p.
    [Discusses possibility of reopening of Provincetown Players with a new group of people; expresses ideas on how this group should be composed.]
  - Jig ( George Cram Cook) to Edna Kenton, 1922 May 29; AN, 1 p.
    [Supplements Susan Glaspell's letter to Kenton; criticizes it.]
  - Edna Kenton to Jig ( George Cram Cook ), Susan Glaspell, and "Gene" [Eugene?] O'Neill, [1922] January 22; TL, 2 p.
    [Proposes fundraising possibilities for the theater, such as a dinner, a ball, etc.; mentions Mr. Faust and The Ape.]
  - Susan Glaspell to Edna Kenton, [1922] May 11; TLS, 4 p.
    [Includes autograph postscript; expresses fears that a play may not run long; invites her to come to Greece; requests a copy of
    Thus Spake Zarathustra
    in English.]
  - Susan Glaspell to Edna Kenton, [1922] May 29; TL, 3 p.
    [Includes autograph postscript, signed, written in part by George Cram Cook; remarks about Provincetown Players ' opening night; says he is pleased with reviews; complains that cashier's royalty check has not arrived yet; reports on lovely outing with "Phil" and friends; tells of Jig's drunken adventures in Athens.]
  - Susan Glaspell to Edna Kenton, [1922] June 26; TLS, 2 p.
    [Includes an autograph postscript of [1922] July 2; says she had a wonderful time in camp on Parnassus; confirms arrival of requested copy of
    , and arrival of a script.]
  - Edna Kenton to Jig and Sue ( George Cram Cook and Susan Glaspell ), [1922] July 7; ALS, 2 p.
    [Reports on a committee meeting concerning Provincetown Players; mentions actors and financial backers of theater.]
  - George Cram Cook and Susan Glaspell to Edna Kenton, [1922] n. d.; ALS, 2 p.
    [Confirms arrival of her letters with first news of
    describes Athens and its intellectual atmosphere; expresses appreciation for work well done; Glaspell says she is relieved that Ralph Stuart produced her play.]
  - Susan Glaspell to Edna Kenton, [1925] January 12; TLS, 2 p.
    [Tries to explain her emotional state, her frustration in writing about Jig ( George Cram Cook ) after his death; asks her to write about Jig and the Provincetown Players, his upbringing, his life.]
- Miscellaneous
  - New York Morning Telegraph, "The Story of Susan Glaspell" by Alice Rohe, 1921 December 18; Interview,
    [Glaspell admits to being interested in all progressive movements, feminist social or economic.]
  - New York Herald review of Susan Glaspell's Chains of Dew, 1922 April 28; Review,
    [Reviews the comedy which satirizes bobbed hair and birth control; credits the play with much wit and an occasional line on birth control that hovered "on the verge," according to Glaspell.]